<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>The blog of CakePHP.nu</title>
 <link href="http://cakephp.nu/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://cakephp.nu"/>
 <updated>2013-09-07T03:50:11+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://cakephp.nu</id>
 <author>
   <name>CakePHP.nu</name>
   <email>jippignu@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Slides from my talks at CakeFest 2013</title>
   <link href="http://cakephp.nu/2013/09/06/cakefest-2013.html"/>
   <updated>2013-09-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://cakephp.nu/2013/09/06/cakefest-2013</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The slides for my 3 talks at CakeFest 2013 are now online&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='scaling_cakephp'&gt;&lt;a href='http://friendsofcake.com/presentations/cakefest-2013/scaling-cakephp'&gt;Scaling CakePHP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A talk on scaling CakePHP. It got surprisingly little to do with CakePHP, and so much more to do with PHP and the underlying infrastructure for your servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='crud__application_development_on_steroids'&gt;&lt;a href='http://friendsofcake.com/crud/presentations/jippi-cakefest-2013/'&gt;Crud - Application Development on steroids&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk on &lt;a href='https://github.com/friendsofcake/crud'&gt;CRUD&lt;/a&gt;, describing the pro and cons of bake, scaffolding and CRUD, and how awesome CRUD really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='friends_of_cake'&gt;&lt;a href='http://friendsofcake.com/presentations/cakefest-2013/friends-of-cake/'&gt;Friends Of Cake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented the vision for &lt;a href='http://friendsofcake.com/'&gt;Friends Of Cake&lt;/a&gt; and what we want to achieve with the project and how it can benefit the CakePHP community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro tip&lt;/strong&gt;: press &amp;#8220;s&amp;#8221; on the presentation page to see my speaker notes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>open_basedir will slow you down &#8211; security vs. speed</title>
   <link href="http://cakephp.nu/2008/03/21/open_basedir-will-slow-you-down-security-vs-speed.html"/>
   <updated>2008-03-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://cakephp.nu/2008/03/21/open_basedir-will-slow-you-down-security-vs-speed</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just a quickie on lighttpd and open_basedir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on some security enhancements for my new website project, and in that progress, I have moved away from Apache2.2.3 and now using Lighttpd instead. Lighttpd does not use the same method of invoking php as apache does (mod_php vs. fast-cgi php).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my eager to make the application as secure and locked down as possible, I went berserk in the php-cgi.ini file and turned on just about any security feature I could find (not safemode!), including the innocent looking switch called “open_basedir”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was rather late in the night, so when I resumed my work the following day, I have long forgotten about all the fancy security settings I had enabled in php.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few hours ago I noticed that the complete render time for the front page suddenly was ~2seconds(!) &amp;#8211; and comparing with apache’s load time for the same page (0.9s) I was quite disappointed at lighttpd and fastcgi, but refused to give up my new found love without a fair trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attacked google with full force without finding any useful resources that might be able to explain my issue.. I was quite sure it was APC that did not function well in a fastcgi environment &amp;#8211; and therefore my google madness was focused around the keywords “apc + fastcgi”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While chatting to PatrickDK in the #lighttpd channel @ freenode, it suddenly hit me &amp;#8211; let’s try to disable everything I have “fixed” last night &amp;#8211; starting with XDebug, some 3rd party php modules (syck, memcache, simplexml, fileinfo) &amp;#8211; and then, open_basedir flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And with just one line commented out in my php-cgi.ini file, the render time went from 2.4 to 0.5 seconds !!(!!)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just a little note to you guys out there, beware of the open_basedir setting in a setup where you include many files, it is a rather costly feature to use. And when running fastcgi php in chroot()ed setup, its not really required anyway&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Its another +1 for lighty and fastcgi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I’m aware that open_basedir is slow because it has to validate EVERY file or path you work with inside php to check if its within the scope defined.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New books from amazon.co.uk</title>
   <link href="http://cakephp.nu/2008/03/19/books-amazoncouk.html"/>
   <updated>2008-03-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://cakephp.nu/2008/03/19/books-amazoncouk</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just got an email from Amazon.co.uk &amp;#8211; the have shipped my new batch of dev-books :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time around it was more an impulze to buy some books, so I hope I will end up as satisfied as last time I purchased some books from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li /&gt;

&lt;li /&gt;

&lt;li /&gt;

&lt;li /&gt;

&lt;li /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably give a short review of the books once I have read them ;)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CakePHP 1.2 beta has been released</title>
   <link href="http://cakephp.nu/2008/01/02/cakephp-12-beta-released.html"/>
   <updated>2008-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://cakephp.nu/2008/01/02/cakephp-12-beta-released</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Finally it happened ! &lt;strong&gt;CakePHP 1.2 beta&lt;/strong&gt; has been released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the new stuff includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reverse routing for array based urls&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;RESTful automagic&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Forms are easier to create and maintain&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Security enhancements for better CSRF prevention and HTTP Authentication&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;CookieComponent for securely storing persistent data on the client side&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Model behaviors&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The &amp;#8220;with&amp;#8221; key allows you to define a dynamic join table model&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Pagination of model records with an extensive helper&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Internationalization and Localization&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Authentication component&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Configure class to provide dynamic handling of configuration settings&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Cache Engine (memcache, xcache, apc, model, file)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Console&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View the rest of the changes at &lt;a href='http://bakery.cakephp.org/articles/view/new-year-new-beta' target='_blank'&gt;the bakery announcement&lt;/a&gt; made by PHPnut&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using the 1.2 branch for more than a year now, and it has been a real pleasure to see how development has moved in a very interested direction. Being in the -dev channel I have also been able to follow some of the discussions on what can stay and what can go. The result, a very clean codebase with a lot of cool features, that is very easy (and &lt;strong&gt;fast!&lt;/strong&gt;) to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my personal favorites has to be the new ModelBehavior feature. Its incredible easy to work with, and makes its very easy to add new features to a already running project without having to hack your way into either Cake or App code :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the few things I miss is the possibility to return a result set in Model::beforeFind &amp;#8211; so it would be possible to create a simple cache mechanism for your query data (together with the new cache engines). Its possible, but requires a little bit of overloading of Model::find to get it to play nicely, oh well :)&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CakeFest website launched!</title>
   <link href="http://cakephp.nu/2008/01/02/cakefest-website-launched.html"/>
   <updated>2008-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://cakephp.nu/2008/01/02/cakefest-website-launched</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just in on google group &amp;#8211; the cake fest website has been launched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://www.cakefest.org/' target='_blank'&gt;Head over to the cakefest website and join the fun&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cakefest is the first global meetup for CakePHP (and probably also other PHP programmers) ever, so its going to be very excited&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
